Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Milton Avery papers
1926-1982 (bulk 1950-1982)
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
AAA.avermilt
Avery, Milton
2.8 linear feet
The papers of abstract painter Milton Avery measure 2.8 linear feet and date from 1926 to 1982, with the bulk of the collection dating from 1950 to 1982. Almost the entire collection consists of records of the Milton Avery Trust (2.4 linear feet) maintained by Avery's wife Sally, who served as a trustee. Milton Avery's business and personal correspondence (five folders) contains letters from friends and fellow artists, including a few from George Duthuit, Louis Eilshemius, Marsden Hartley, Wallace Putnam, and Mark Rothko. Also found are scattered writings about Avery, price lists, estate records, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and news clippings.
Biographical Note
Milton Avery (1885-1965) was born in Altmar, New York and grew up in Hartford, Connecticut. Around 1905 he began attending the Connecticut League of Art Students in Hartford where he studied life drawing while also working full-time as a factory worker and file clerk. In 1915 he had his first public exhibition and, in 1918, transferred to the School of Art Society in Hartford. In 1924 he met Sally Michel (1905-2003), a student at the Art Students League in New York, and moved to New York City to be closer to her. They married one year later. Around this time Avery also altered his year of birth to 1893, perhaps due to the age difference between him and Sally. After their marriage Sally worked as an illustrator so that Avery could paint full time.
During the early 1920s, Avery's works were traditional figurative and genre subjects, influenced by American Impressionism. By the mid 1920s, with his move to New York, Avery began to simplify his forms and use broader expanses of flat color. Although his paintings became increasingly abstract, he never fully abandoned representational subject matter, painting figure groups, still lifes, landscapes, and seascapes. By the mid-1940s, Avery's work was characterized by a reduction of elements and elimination of detail, filled with an emphasis on arbitrary color.
Avery exhibited in a group show at The Opportunity Gallery in 1928 which also featured Mark Rothko and the two became close friends. He became friends with many other artists including Adolph Gottlieb, Barnett Newman, and Marsden Hartley. Avery's color work was an important influence on many younger artists, particularly Mark Rothko, Adolph Gottlieb, Barnett Newman, Helen Frankenthaler, and other Color Field painters. The Phillips Collection in Washington, D.C. was the first museum to purchase one of his paintings in 1929 and to give him his first solo museum exhibition in 1944.
In 1949 Milton Avery suffered a major heart attack and began making monotypes during his recovery. He returned to painting despite periods of ill-health, and his reputation grew rapidly over the next ten years, culminating in a retrospective at the Whitney Museum of American Art in New York in 1960. He also exhibited along with his wife Sally Avery and their daughter, March Avery Cavanaugh (born in 1932), both of whom were also painters. Avery died in 1965 and left behind an oeuvre of paintings that numbers in the thousands. His wife Sally managed his estate and the sale of his works to many major museums, and served as a trustee for the Milton Avery Trust until her death in 2003.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of abstract painter Milton Avery measure 2.8 linear feet and date from 1926 to 1982, with the bulk of the collection dating from 1950 to 1982. Almost the entire collection consists of business files maintained by Milton Avery's wife Sally as a trustee for the Milton Avery Trust (2.4 linear feet). Milton Avery's business and personal correspondence (five folders) contains letters from friends and fellow artists, including a few from George Duthuit, Louis Eilshemius, Marsden Hartley, Wallace Putnam, and Mark Rothko. Also found are scattered writings about Avery, price lists, estate records, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and news clippings.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 7 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1964, 1975 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1935-1981 (Box 1; 10 folders)
Series 3: Subject Files, 1950-1981 (Box 1-4; 2.4 linear feet)
Series 4: Writings, circa 1951-1979 (Box 4; 5 folders)
Series 5: Financial & Legal Records, 1943-1982 (Box 4; 6 folders)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1926, 1962-1977 (Box 4; 4 folders)
Series 7: Photographs, circa 1970 (Box 4; 1 folder)
Index Terms
This collection is indexed under the following index terms in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art.
Subjects-Topical:
Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Painting, Abstract
Names:
Avery, Sally; Duthuit, Georges, 1891-; Putnam, Wallace, 1899-; Hartley, Marsden, 1877-1943; Eilshemius, Louis M. (Louis Michel), 1864-1941; Rothko, Mark, 1903-1970
Provenance
The Milton Avery papers were donated in 1968, 1969, and 1982 by his widow Sally Avery, including a few letters previously loaned for microfilming.
Separated Material
Scrapbooks, a sketchbook, Christmas cards, exhibition catalogs, photographs, and correspondence were loaned between 1968 and 1982 for microfilming by Sally Avery. Loaned material is available for viewing on microfilm reels N68-95, N68-115, N69-63, and 2535, but is not described in the container listing of this finding aid.
Restrictions on Access
The collection has been digitized and is available online via the Archives of American Art's website.
Alternative Forms Available
The collection was digitized in 2007 and is available via the Archives of American Art's website.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1964, 1975, Series 1:; (Box 1; 1 folder)
  One folder containing a list of Milton Avery anecdotes, excerpts from reviews, a brief biographical note, a certificate from the National Council of Jewish Women, and a brief list of biographical sources.
  - Biographical Material, 1964, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1935-1981, Series 2:; (Box 1; 10 folders)
  Correspondence consists of five folders of letters to Milton Avery and correspondence with Sally Avery and the Milton Avery Trust. Letters to Milton Avery consist of letters from people purchasing works of art, including Joseph Hirshhorn, letters from art galleries concerning the exhibition or purchase of artwork, requests for information from researchers or journalists, and several letters of congratulations for the 1960 Whitney Museum of American Art retrospective. Also found are a few letters from friends and fellow artists, including Mark Rothko, Louis Eilshemius, Marsden Hartley, Wallace Putnam, and George Duthuit.
  Sally Avery's correspondence, often addressed to the Milton Avery Trust, is primarily business correspondence regarding the handling of her husband's legacy of artwork. Included are letters with individuals, galleries, and museums regarding sales and loans. Other topics include research questions, thanking her for visits, and congratulations for exhibitions. Although most of the correspondence is incoming, there are also scattered copies of outgoing correspondence. A large amount of similar business correspondence is also filed in Series 2: Subject Files.
  - Letters to Milton Avery, 19--, 1935-1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters to Milton Avery, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters to Milton Avery, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters to Milton Avery, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Sally Avery (Milton Avery Trust) correspondence, 1946-1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Sally Avery (Milton Avery Trust) correspondence, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Sally Avery (Milton Avery Trust) correspondence, 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Sally Avery (Milton Avery Trust) correspondence, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Sally Avery (Milton Avery Trust) correspondence, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Sally Avery (Milton Avery Trust) correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Subject Files, 1950-1981, Series 3:; (Box 1-4; 2.4 linear feet)
  Subject files consist of alphabetical business files maintained by Sally Avery for art galleries, museums, collectors, colleges and universities, and other art organizations which exhibited or purchased works by Milton Avery. Files contain a wide variety of documentation, including correspondence between the organization and Sally Avery, loan agreements, exhibition or sales receipts, lists of artworks, price lists, legal documents, and printed material such as news clippings and exhibition announcements. Although most of the files are for sales and loans, some of the files are for art galleries which represented and sold Avery's work, such as the Grace Borgenicht Gallery and Gallery Reese Palley. Also found in this series is a file Sally Avery kept regarding published biographies of Milton Avery. Files are arranged alphabetically by either name or topic and documents are arranged chronologically within each folder.
  - Achim Moeller Ltd., 1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Addison-Wesley Publishing Company, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Akron Art Institute, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Aldis Browne Fine Arts, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Allentown Art Museum, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Alpha Gallery, 1969-1979, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 17-20)
  - American Federation of Arts (Milton Avery Retrospective), 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - American Federation of Arts, 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - American Embassy, Prague, 1966-1970 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Andre Emmerich Gallery, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Arkansas Art Center, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Associated American Artists, 1963-1980, (7 folders) (Box 1, Folder 26-32)
  - Association of Contemporary Artists Galleries, 1968-1981 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Barbara Mathes Gallery, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Bard College, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Biographies of Milton Avery, 1969-1979 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Bonfoey Company, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Cape Split Place, Inc., 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Carl Solway Gallery (Flair Gallery), 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Charles H. Scott Gallery (Emily Carr College of Art), 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Charles E. Slatkin, Inc. Galleries, 1968-1980 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Cleveland Museum of Art, 1971, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - College of Wooster, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Comsky Gallery, 1972-1979, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 44-45)
  - Connecticut Fine Arts, Inc., 1973-1979 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - David Gallery, 1971-1978 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - David Mirvish Gallery, 1967-1978, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 48-50)
  - Dayton Art Institute, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Donald Morris Gallery, 1958-1980, (8 folders) (Box 1, Folder 52-59)
  - Edmonton Art Gallery, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Esther Stuttman Gallery, 1965-1973 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Everson Museum of Art, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Felix Landau Gallery, 1956-1965 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Fogg Museum, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Fontana Gallery, 1969-1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Forum Gallery, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Galerie Beyeler, 1971-1976 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Galerie du Jonelle, 1966-1974 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Galerie Internationale, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Gallery 14, 1960-1967 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Gallery Reese Palley, 1964-1972, (6 folders) (Box 2, Folder 9-14)
  - Gimpel Fils, Ltd., 1973-1976 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Grace Borgenicht Gallery, 1951-1977, 1980, (6 folders) (Box 2, Folder 16-21)
  - Graphics International Ltd. (Lunn Gallery), 1971-1979, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 22-25)
  - Greenberg Gallery, 1973-1982 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Guggenheim Museum, 1965, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Gump's Gallery, 1964-1968 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Harmon Gallery, 1965-1970 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Heritage Plantation of Sandwich, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Hirschl & Adler Galleries, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Hirshhorn Museum & Sculpture Garden, 1971-1980 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Indianapolis Museum of Art, 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - International Exhibition Foundation, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - International Gallery, Inc., 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Jack Fader Collection, 1971-1975 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Jane Haslem Gallery, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Jarvis Gallery, 1972-1978 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Joan Whitney Payson Gallery of Art, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - John and Mable Ringling Museum of Art, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Katonah Gallery, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Kay Kaz Gallery, 1965-1969 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Lehigh University, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Little Gallery (Janet Fleisher), 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Louisiana Gallery, 1968-1981, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 45-47)
  - MacDowell Gallery, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Makler Gallery, 1960-1980, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 49-51)
  - Marianne Friedland Gallery, 1976-1979 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Mattatuck Museum, 1967-1971 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Metropolitan Opera Association, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Michael Berger Gallery, 1973-1980 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Michigan State University, 1969, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Mid-American Arts Alliance, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Minnesota Museum of Art, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - M. Knodler & Co., 1950-1979 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Mobile Art Gallery, 1964-1969 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Museum of Fine Arts, Houston, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Museum of Modern Art, 1961-1971, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - New Britain Museum of American Art, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - New York WPA Artists, Inc., 1977 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Noah Goldowsky Inc., 1969-1973 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Paintings & Drawings Ltd., 1964-1977 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Parliament Gallery, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Pasadena Art Museum, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Philadelphia Museum of Art, 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Phillips Collection, 1965, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Pratt Graphics Center, 1973, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Princeton University Library, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Richard Gray Gallery, 1971-1976 (Box 3 (hol), Folder 1)
  - Robert Hull Fleming Museum, University of Vermont, 1976 (Box 3 (hol), Folder 2)
  - Rudolph Gallery, 1959-1970 (Box 3 (hol), Folder 3)
  - Sears, Roebuck and Co., 1965 (Box 3 (hol), Folder 4)
  - Shore Studio Galleries, 1961 (Box 3 (hol), Folder 5)
  - Smithsonian Institution, 1972-1974, 1979 (Box 3 (hol), Folder 6)
  - Society of the Four Arts, 1977-1978 (Box 3 (hol), Folder 7)
  - Southern Methodist University, Meadows Museum & University Gallery, 1980-1981 (Box 3 (hol), Folder 8)
  - Sterling & Francine Clark Art Institute, 1978-1981 (Box 3 (hol), Folder 9)
  - Strathcona, 1980 (Box 3 (hol), Folder 10)
  - Summit Art Center, 1975-1977 (Box 3 (hol), Folder 11)
  - Syracuse University, 1970, 1972-1973 (Box 3 (hol), Folder 12)
  - Tanglewood Gallery, 1959-1965 (Box 3 (hol), Folder 13)
  - Terry Dintenfass, Inc. (Contemporary Paintings), 1959-1965 (Box 3 (hol), Folder 14)
  - Thomas Gibson Fine Art Ltd., 1973-1979 (Box 3 (hol), Folder 15)
  - Thorne Art Gallery (Keene State College), 1970-1973 (Box 3 (hol), Folder 16)
  - Tirca Karlis Gallery, 1965-1976 (Box 3 (hol), Folder 17)
  - University of California, Irvine, 1970-1971 (Box 3 (hol), Folder 18)
  - University of California, Santa Barbara, 1979-1980 (Box 3 (hol), Folder 19)
  - University of Oregon, 1968-1969 (Box 3 (hol), Folder 20)
  - University of Texas at Austin, 1975-1977 (Box 3 (hol), Folder 21)
  - Vassar College Art Gallery, 1970-1977 (Box 3 (hol), Folder 22)
  - Waddington Galleries, 1962-1972, (5 folders) (Box 3 (hol), Folder 23-27)
  - Waddington Galleries, 1973-1974, (2 folders) (Box 4 (hol), Folder 1-2)
  - Wadsworth Atheneum, 1962-1964 (Box 4 (hol), Folder 3)
  - Webb & Parsons Gallery, 1974-1979 (Box 4 (hol), Folder 4)
  - Western Electric, Corporate Education Organization, 1979 (Box 4 (hol), Folder 5)
  - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1966, 1979-1980 (Box 4 (hol), Folder 6)
  - Wichita State University, 1974-1977 (Box 4 (hol), Folder 7)
  - William Benton Museum of Art, 1975-1976 (Box 4 (hol), Folder 8)
  - William Zierler, Inc., 1968-1976 (Box 4 (hol), Folder 9)
  - Woodstock Artists Association, 1977 (Box 4 (hol), Folder 10)
  - Woodward Foundation, 1963-1972 (Box 4 (hol), Folder 11)
  - Yares Gallery, 1976-1978 (Box 4 (hol), Folder 12)
- Writings about Avery, circa 1951-1979, Series 4:; (Box 4; 5 folders)
  Writings consist of essays about Milton Avery, including a draft essay by Wolf Kahn for the Art Journal, a few poems written by Aaron Cohen describing certain paintings by Avery, and a few notes written by Sally Avery. Also found are a typescript and handwritten draft of a tribute to Avery written by Mark Rothko shortly after Avery's death.
  - Aaron E. Cohen, Poetry, circa 1951 (Box 4 (hol), Folder 13)
  - Wolf Kahn, "Milton Avery's Good Example," circa 1979 (Box 4 (hol), Folder 14)
  - Annette and Louis Kaufman, "Milton Avery: Fauve Portraitist", circa 1960 (Box 4 (hol), Folder 15)
  - Mark Rothko, Written Tribute to Avery, circa 1965 (Box 4 (hol), Folder 16)
  - Notes by Sally Avery, circa 1970 (Box 4 (hol), Folder 17)
- Financial & Legal Records, 1943-1982, Series 5:; (Box 4; 6 folders)
  Found here is a photocopy of Milton Avery's Last Will and Testament, a detailed appraisal of nearly 1000 works of art in the Milton Avery estate, price lists, and a small number of loan forms and sales receipts. Also found is one folder of the legal and financial records of the Milton Avery Estate.
  - Last Will and Testament, 1962 (Box 4 (hol), Folder 18)
  - Estate Appraisal of Artwork, 1965 (Box 4 (hol), Folder 19)
  - Price Lists, 1960-1974, (2 folders) (Box 4 (hol), Folder 20-21)
  - Milton Avery Estate Legal and Financial Records, 1962-1972 (Box 4 (hol), Folder 22)
  - Artwork Loans and Sales Receipts, 1943-1982 (Box 4 (hol), Folder 23)
- Printed Material, 1926, 1962-1977, Series 6:; (Box 4; 4 folders)
  Printed Material focuses primarily on Avery's later career and legacy. Included are exhibition announcements and catalogs, news clippings, various brochures, bulletins, and other announcements.
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1966-1973 (Box 4 (hol), Folder 24)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1926, 1966-1977 (Box 4 (hol), Folder 25)
  - News Clippings, 1963-1973 (Box 4 (hol), Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1962-1974, (Not scanned) (Box 4 (hol), Folder 27)
- Photographs, circa 1970, Series 7:; (Box 4; 1 folder)
  This series contains five photographs of an unidentified exhibition of photography that does not include Avery's artwork.
  - Photographs of an Unidentified Exhibition, circa 1970, (Not scanned) (Box 4 (hol), Folder 28)